Now we're going to discuss structures of
organizations.
Why this is so important
is that it's going to
determine the level of
power you do or do not have.
And that's very important
because whether or not you
have power, your head is
still on the chopping block.
Yeah, I'm being a little dramatic there,
but you are ultimately responsible for
your project, even if you don't have any
power.
So keep that in mind.
All right.
If we look at the second slide here,
I'm going to start with a functional
organization and then move into matrix to
project ties.
We'll start with functional, where you see
over on the left side of the slide,
where we have the least amount of power
until we get to the most amount of power.
So a functional organization structure,
a picture an org chart.
You've got your CEO, senior executives,
and then functional managers, marketing,
manager, finance manager, production
manager, etc.
So let's say you are a marketing
specialist.
You land a marketing project typically.
It's going to be within your department.
All right.
You report to the marketing manager,
that functional manager.
So this is the organizational structure
where you have the least amount of power.
The functional manager
will be telling you what
the project is, what the
scope of the project is.
How long you have, how much time.
time you have, the resources you have to
use.
So you have little to know authority here.
The functional manager is calling all the
shots.
Now let's move into a matrix organization.
So the organizational structure is set up
similarly, but here where you report to
the functional manager
still, same with your
resources, usually between
different departments.
Your resources will
report to those functional
managers as well as you for your projects.
So here, the functional managers still
have all the power.
You still report to the functional
manager.
So do all the resources who also report to
you for this project.
You have little to know authority.
The functional manager is calling the
shots.
Usually working between departments here
though, all right?
The next matrix organizational structure
we're talking about is balanced and this
is where we have a balance of power
between you and this is where you
officially get the title of project
manager you and the functional manager
meaning the marketing manager for example
you still report to that marketing manager
but now most of the time you are focused
on the project a lot of times full time
whereas a functional manager day in day
out they are focused on operations.
So this is where the most contention will
be here too.
Your focus is the project and that's your
responsibility.
All right.
You're trying to get
that project done, but the
functional manager is
trying to get operations done.
And remember, you report to the functional
manager, so do the resources.
Okay, so this is where the most contention
will be.
You're trying to get your project done.
You still report to that
functional manager,
okay, who's focused
on operations every day.
Then we move up to a strong matrix.
And what's different about this one, we
have a separate vertical structure here.
The project management office,
PMO, project management office.
All the project managers report to the PMO
here.
Okay, we are no longer reporting to
functional managers.
So this is where we have the most power in
a matrix organization, a strong matrix.
We report to the PMO.
We'll be assigned a project by the PMO.
And this is where you'll have the most
authority in a matrix organization.
All right.
Now we move to projectized.
So this organizational structure,
the focus is projects, day in, day out.
Okay?
Okay.
So this is where you have, as the PM,
ultimate power.
You report directly to the CEO or a senior
executive.
Functional managers are not in the way.
Neither are PMOs.
Okay.
So you have the ultimate authority here.
You'll work directly
with the stakeholders to
figure out what the
scope of the project is.
Based on the scope,
how long it's going to take,
how much it's going to
cost, the resources you need.
You'll do the hiring and firing here.
Okay, so this is where you have the
ultimate power.
All right, let's look at this next slide.
When you go back to study, do focus on
from the functional through project ties.
That's your focus, which is what we just
covered.
And whether or not you have power,
whether you are part-time or when you get
to a balanced, usually part-time to
full-time on a project, and when your
resources are going to be available for
your project as well.
I do want to cover while we're here,
though.
Let's look over on the left top,
organic or simple organization structures.
So those are usually a small, it could be
a startup organization or just a small
organization that works on functional
areas and will land some projects.
Way over on the right, well, next to last,
virtual organizations.
These are organizations.
that have no or a small amount of
face-to-face interaction.
They're usually not co-located,
meaning all in the same location.
Little to know face-to-face interaction,
okay?
That's why communication technology is so
important using go-to meetings,
Zoom meetings, Microsoft meetings,
all those types of things.
If you are not face-to-face, co-locating.
you need to be able to see each other.
Okay, that's really important.
And then we have last hybrid.
So that's a mixture.
So you could have a functional
organizational structure.
Again, the organization is focused on
operations day in, day
out, what they do best.
Well, the organization
can take a different path,
decide they want to work
on more projects, for example.
And, And they can create a
PMO, a project management
office, where now you'll have
a strong matrix organization.
So functional with a
strong matrix organization
arm or move to a strong matrix matrix.
So a hybrid is a mixture.
You can change depending on what the
organization's objectives are.
All right.
All these things to keep in mind.